Guide to the Mary Barnard Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Mary Barnard papers
1890-2001
1933-2001
YCAL MSS 524
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
20.21
(24 boxes) + 1 broadside
The papers document the life and literary career of Mary Barnard and consist of writings, correspondence, travel papers, diaries, photographs, and audiovisual materials, dating from the 1890s to 2001. Writings include drafts of published and unpublished works, research materials, and notebooks. Correspondence pertains mostly to Barnard's writing career and personal relationships, but also includes family correspondence. Correspondents include Ezra and Dorothy Pound and William Carlos Williams. Travel papers include diaries written by Barnard, passports, brochures, maps and printed ephemera. The collection also includes a small amount of daily calendars, photograph albums, artwork, and audio and video cassettes.
Barnard, Mary
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 18 (artwork) Boxes 19-20 (audio and video tapes): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Elizabeth Bell, 2002.
Purchased from Elizabeth Bell on the Eugene G. O'Neill Memorial Fund, 2005.
Arrangement
Organized into six series: I. Writings, 1932-1999. II. Correspondence, 1909-2001. III. Travel Papers, 1949-1994. IV. Calendars and Address Books, 1959-2001. V. Photographs, 1890s-1990s. VI. Other Papers, 1933-2001.
Mary Barnard, 1909-2001
American poet, biographer, and translator Mary Ethel Barnard was born in Vancouver, Washington on December 6, 1909. She was the daughter of Bertha Hoard and Samuel Melvin Barnard, who worked in the timber industry. After graduating from Reed College in 1932, Barnard established a relationship by mail with Ezra Pound, who became her literary mentor. Her poetry, prose, and translations of Greek poetry were published in literary magazines and as monographs. She was awarded numerous honors throughout her career, including the Levinson Award (1936), the Elliston Award (1979), and the Western States Book Award for Poetry (1986). Barnard died in 2001.
Scope and Contents
The papers document the life and literary career of Mary Barnard and consist of writings, correspondence, travel papers, diaries, photographs, artwork, and audiovisual materials, dating from the 1890s to 2001.Writings include drafts of published and unpublished works, research materials, and notebooks. Correspondence pertains mostly to Barnard's writing career and personal relationships, but also includes family correspondence. Correspondents include Ezra and Dorothy Pound and William Carlos Williams. Travel papers include diaries written by Barnard, passports, brochures, maps and printed ephemera. The collection also includes a small amount of daily calendars, photograph albums, artwork, and audio and video cassettes.
American poetry -- 20th Century; Greek poetry -- Translations into English; Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Translators; Audiocassettes; Audiovisual materials; Photographic prints; Videocassettes; Poets; Translators; Barnard, Mary; Pound, Dorothy; Pound, Ezra, 1885-1972; Williams, William Carlos, 1883-1963
- Writings, 1932-1999; Series I; 4.83 linear feet (6 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I contains drafts of poetry, prose, and translations of Greek poetry (all chiefly typescript), with a small amount of printed material and correspondence related to the writings. The series also includes research files consisting chiefly of notes and clippings.
  Arrangement
  Organized into three subseries: Titled Works, Untitled Works, and Research Files.
  - Titled Works
    Arranged alphabetically by title.
    - Ashe Knoll
      - First copy, typescript carbon, undated; 2 (Box 1)
      - Second copy, typescript, undated; 2 (Box 1)
    - Assault on Mt. Helicon
      - Draft, typescript, corrected, circa 1984; 3 folders (Box 1)
      - Indexing proof and uncorrected page proof, circa 1984 (Box 1)
      - Red notebook used in organizing book, circa 1984 (Box 1)
    - "Barnard I," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 1)
    - "Barnard II," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 1)
    - "The Case of the Bottled Twins," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 1)
    - "The Cat," radio play, typescript, 1947 (Box 1)
    - "The Distaff Side," typescript, undated (Box 1)
    - Erato
      - Typescript, corrected, proof, and correspondence, 1998-1999; 2 (Box 1)
      - Second draft of John's introduction, typescript, 1998 (Box 1)
    - First Six Fyttes, xerox copy, undated (Box 1)
    - The Horae of Mary Ethel Barnard, typescripts, 1932, undated; 2; s (Box 1)
    - "How to Make a Mythomorph," proof, 1966 (Box 1)
    - The Iliad (translation into English)
      - Books I-V, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 2)
      - Books I and III, carbon copy, undated (Box 2)
      - Books I and III, fair copy, undated (Box 2)
      - Book IV, corrected copy, undated (Box 2)
      - Book V, first draft, undated (Box 2)
      - Book V, draft corrected, undated (Box 2)
      - Loose typescript pages, undated (Box 2)
      - Loose typescript pages, translations, comments, undated (Box 2)
    - "Mazes," research material and typescript notes, undated (Box 2)
    - The Mythmakers
      - Typescript carbon, circa 1966; 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Third copy, typescript carbon, circa 1966; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Nantucket Genesis, typescript, corrected, circa 1988 (Box 2)
    - A Pagan's Guide to Frescoes
      - Outline, introduction and draft of two chapters, typescript, undated (Box 2)
      - Book notes, typescript, undated; 2 (Box 2)
      - Pictures, undated (Box 2)
      - Introduction, typescript carbon, undated (Box 2)
    - "Phaistos Disk," typescript notes, 1953 (Box 2)
    - "The Prison and The Key," typescript, undated (Box 2)
    - Sappho: A New Translation, typescripts, circa 1958; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Swamp Lake, typescript carbon, undated; 2 (Box 3)
    - "Time - prose," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 3)
    - "Time and Symbolism," typescript, xerox copies, and clippings related to topic, undated (Box 3)
    - "Time and Tradition," typescript and research materials, undated; 2 (Box 3)
    - Time and The White Tigress
      - Corrected typescripts and illustrations, circa 1986; 5 (Box 3)
      - "Working manuscript," typescript and manuscript, circa 1986; 2 (Box 3)
      - "Bibliographies Tigress, etc.," typescript, circa 1986 (Box 3)
      - Index cards for research, circa 1986 (Box 21)
    - "The Trap," typescript carbon, 1940 (Box 3)
  - Untitled Works
    - Illustrations and correspondence by Anita Bigelow, undated; 4 (Box 3)
    - Working versions of poems and translations, typescript and manuscript, undated; 3 (Box 4)
    - Unidentified writings, undated; 2 (Box 4)
  - Research Files
    - Notes on "Moon Myth," "Personae," and "Theorizing", undated; 3 (Box 4)
    - Notes on "Calendars," "Festivals," "Dragons," "Mummy," "Miscellaneous", undated; 2 (Box 4)
    - Notes on mythology, undated; 2 (Box 4)
    - Notes on the zodiac, undated (Box 4)
    - Poems, typescript, undated (Box 4)
    - Quotations and notes on festivals, undated (Box 4)
    - Quotations, undated (Box 4)
    - Notes on "Drinks and Drugs," "Star Craft," and "Eclipses", undated; 2 (Box 4)
    - Notes on astronomy, undated; 2 (Box 4)
    - Notes on "Shamanism," "Soul Journeys," "Trees," "Water of Life," and "Center/Axis", undated; 2 (Box 4)
    - College notebooks, 1930s; 2 (Box 5)
    - Pages from diaries, undated; 3 (Box 5)
- Correspondence, 1909-2001; Series II; 9 linear feet (9 boxes)
  Series II contains the family and general correspondence of Mary Barnard, spanning 1909 to 2001. It contains primarily incoming correspondence, with a small amount of outgoing correspondence, both copies and originals. Principal correspondents include Marianne Moore, Winifred Overhoser, Dorothy Pound, Ezra Pound, and William Carlos Williams. In addition to letters, postcards, and other correspondence to and from Mary Barnard are a small amount of clippings and printed material, scattered writings by Barnard and others, genealogical research materials, and personal papers.
  Organized into two subseries: Family Correspondence and General Correspondence.
  - Family Correspondence
    Arranged roughly chronologically.
    - Early letters from Ocean Park, Seattle, San Francisco, L.A., 1930s (Box 6)
    - New York and Yaddo, 1936; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - New York and Yaddo, 1938; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - New York, Spring 1939 (Box 6)
    - Letters from Lake School House and University of California, Summer 1939 (Box 6)
    - Buffalo, 1939 (Box 6)
    - Family correspondence, 1940-1942; 4 (Box 6)
    - Buffalo, Spring 1943 (Box 6)
    - New York City, Fall 1943 (Box 6)
    - Family correspondence, 1944-1951; 8 (Box 6)
    - Family correspondence, 1952-1953 (Box 7)
    - European correspondence, 1953-1954; 6 (Box 7)
    - Family correspondence, except European letters, 1954 (Box 7)
    - Family correspondece, 1955-1959; 4 (Box 7)
    - Family correspondence, 1989-1993 (Box 7)
    - "Study letters," "Mary Ethel", 1953-1968; 4 (Box 7)
    - "Letters to keep at least temporarily", 1943-1979 (Box 7)
    - Family correspondence, undated; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Carbons of Mary Barnard's letters and/or miscellaneous early letters returned, 1938-1989 (Box 7)
    - Barnard, S. M., 1962, undated (Box 7)
    - "Cargo record", undated (Box 7)
    - Family correspondence, undated; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - General Correspondence
    Not arranged in any particular order.
    - Unidentified, 1940-1999; 11 (Box 8)
    - Pre-publication correspondence with publishers regarding Assault on Mt. Helicon, Sappho, Mythmakers, 1959-1984; 4 (Box 8)
    - Letters from Buffalo, 1940-1984 (Box 8)
    - Cards from desk, 1995-2001 (Box 8)
    - Serly, Tibor, 1959-1984; 3 (Box 8)
    - Letters from editors, rejections, etc., 1934-1980; 2 (Box 9)
    - Kimball, Cynthia, 2000-2001; 2 (Box 9)
    - Northland, Aurora Jeanne, 1988 (Box 9)
    - Sappho, University of California Press correspondence and royalty reports, 1962-1991 (Box 9)
    - Sappho reviews, etc., 1958-1979 (Box 9)
    - Sappho correspondence and clippings, 1984-1999 (Box 9)
    - Assault on Mt. Helicon permissions, 1982 (Box 9)
    - "Medea", 1973-1986 (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous literary, publications, personal appearances, etc., 1934-1984 (Box 9)
    - "Zodiacs", 1991 (Box 9)
    - Literary correspondence, periodicals, bookstores and autographs, 1979; 2 (Box 9)
    - Literary correspondence, 1987-1988; 2 (Box 9)
    - Johnson-Carroll-Hayden family history, 1983-1995; 2 (Box 9)
    - Nantucket Genesis post-publication correspondence, 1989-1996 (Box 9)
    - Census records from L. Hosman re. Marshall Denney, 1996 (Box 9)
    - Nantucket genealogy charts, undated (Box 9)
    - Barnard file correspondence, 1980-1992 (Box 9)
    - Barnard, Charles D., 1981-1990 (Box 9)
    - Nantucket correspondence, 1987-1989 (Box 9)
    - [___], Mary Melissa, 1990-1996; 2 (Box 9)
    - Genealogy, 1980 (Box 9)
    - Barnard file, manuscripts and notes, 1987-1989, undated (Box 9)
    - "Sheila's notes", 1995, undated (Box 9)
    - Family history, undated (Box 9)
    - "William Thomas-Sarah Huffins family of Hancock County Indiana", 1980 (Box 10)
    - Sivetz letter, 1949-1992 (Box 10)
    - B, 1943-1986 (Box 10)
    - C, 1981-1993 (Box 10)
    - D-E, 1984-1987 (Box 10)
    - E-G, 1994 (Box 10)
    - G, 1975-1986 (Box 10)
    - H, 1979-1987 (Box 10)
    - I-L, 1979-1999; 3 (Box 10)
    - M, 1980-1987 (Box 10)
    - N-Q, 1979-1985 (Box 10)
    - Martignori, Marie Louise, 1999 (Box 10)
    - "Papers on Metric", undated (Box 10)
    - R, 1982-1986 (Box 10)
    - S, 1981-1994 (Box 10)
    - T-V, 1979-1984 (Box 10)
    - W-Z, 1969-1994 (Box 10)
    - Western States Book Award for Poetry, 1986 (Box 10)
    - Rachewiltz, Mary de, 1946-1995; 3 (Box 10)
    - Postcards and letters from Ezra Pound, typescript copies, 1933-1938 (Box 10)
    - Kimball, Cynthia, undated (Box 10)
    - Breitenbush Publications, 1978-1993; 3 (Box 10)
    - Western States Arts Foundation, 1985-1987 (Box 10)
    - Ohio University Press-statements, 1967-1977 (Box 11)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 11)
    - Inventories and appraisals, 1964-1998; 2 (Box 11)
    - White, Mary Jane, 1973-1987 (Box 11)
    - Postcards, 1975 (Box 11)
    - Archaeoastronomy, 1981-1983 (Box 11)
    - Calfas, Christine, 2000 (Box 11)
    - Genealogy, undated (Box 11)
    - Genealogy Marshall, undated (Box 11)
    - Miscellaneous, undated; 5 folders (Box 11)
    - Radcliffe College, 1961-1999 (Box 11)
    - Christy, Angela, 1990; 3 folders (Box 11)
    - Ewing, Molly and N.A. Gross, 1991-1997 (Box 11)
    - "Exploration of Voice and Verse: Poetry of Mary Barnard," Thesis by Molly Ewing, 1992 (Box 11)
    - Rejection slips, circa 1928-1938 (Box 11)
    - Sappho-music, Ward Steinman, etc., 1964-1985 (Box 11)
    - Russell and Volkening correspondence/ enclosures, 1945-1986 (Box 11)
    - Laughlin, James, 1935-1981 (Box 11)
    - Fruge, August (mainly regarding Mt. Helicon), 1982-1994; 2 (Box 12)
    - [Hughes?], Dell, 1986 (Box 12)
    - Poems-other people's, undated (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous, 1957-1970, undated (Box 12)
    - Haugaard, Myrna, 1950-1981; 2 (Box 12)
    - Moore, Marianne, 1934-1968; 2 (Box 12)
    - Overholser, Winfred, 1949 March 16 (Box 12)
    - Paige, D. D., 1947-1955 (Box 12)
    - Pound, Dorothy, 1946-1947, undated (Box 12)
    - Pound, Ezra, 1933-1950; 6 (Box 12)
    - Poems from the Burren, undated (Box 12)
    - Poetry/rare books collection at State University of New York, Buffalo, 1974-1994 (Box 12)
    - Bigelow, Anita, 1985 (Box 12)
    - Ludlow, Anne, 1954-1987; 3 (Box 12)
    - Williams, William Carlos, 1935-1967, undated; 3 (Box 12)
    - Wasson, R. Gordon, 1937-1993; 3 (Box 12)
    - Wasson correspondence, copied, 1957-1979; 2 (Box 12)
    - Van Doren, Mark, 1944-1950 (Box 12)
    - Greer, Germaine, 1981-1986 (Box 13)
    - Edwards, John, 1950-1958 (Box 13)
    - James, Edward, 1945-1952, undated (Box 13)
    - Reed College, 1933-1969 (Box 13)
    - Arragon, R. F., 1937-1974 (Box 13)
    - Abbott, Charles D., 1943-1958 (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence regarding publications. Agenda, Rain City, etc., 1987-1993 (Box 13)
    - Rudge, Olga to Viola Jordan, 1946 March 24 (Box 13)
    - Diplomas, birth certificate, 1909-1934 (Box 13)
    - Beginnings (juvenilia) school papers, undated (Box 13)
    - Juvenilia, unpublished poems, undated (Box 13)
    - Poetry manuscripts, early unpublished, etc., undated (Box 13)
    - Literary correspondence, 1986-1999; 2 (Box 13)
    - Medical, 1990-2000 (Box 13)
    - Poems, undated (Box 13)
    - Mythmakers correspondence, 1968-1993 (Box 13)
    - Legal/bank, 1977-1994, undated (Box 13)
    - Time and the White Tigress correspondence, 1984-1986 (Box 13)
    - Sappho correspondence, 1993-1999 (Box 13)
    - Assault on Mt. Helicon correspondence, 1982-1993 (Box 13)
    - Personal correspondence, 1993-2001, undated; 9 (Box 13)
- Travel Papers, 1949-1994; Series III; 1; (1 box)
  Series III consists of material related to Mary Barnard's travels, including correspondence, printed material, notes, travel diaries, and passports.
  - Italy, hotels, correspondence, itineraries, chronicles/France, 1959 (Box 14)
  - Dailey-Thorp travel, 1983 (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous travel papers, 1953-1978, undated (Box 14)
  - Ireland, 1979 (Box 14)
  - Italy, 1978 (Box 14)
  - Publishers' catalogues, 1978-1994 (Box 14)
  - Psychotropic experience-reprints, 1963, 1983 (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous travel papers, undated (Box 14)
  - Towns and provinces, undated (Box 14)
  - Ships, undated; 2 (Box 14)
  - Maps and town plans, undated (Box 14)
  - Individual monuments, undated (Box 14)
  - Travel diaries
    - France and Spain, undated (Box 14)
    - Ireland, undated (Box 14)
    - Italy, 1978 (Box 14)
    - Italy, 1980 (Box 14)
    - New York, 1978 (Box 14)
    - Paris and Provence, 1983 (Box 14)
    - Salzburg and Munich, undated (Box 14)
    - Unidentified travel journals, undated; 5 (Box 14)
  - Passports, 1949-1983; 5 (Box 14)
- Calendars and Address Book, 1959-2001; Series IV; 1; (1 box)
  Arranged chronologically.
  Series IV consists of calendars, daily diaries, and an address book.
  - 1959 (Box 15)
  - 1961 (Box 15)
  - 1964 (Box 15)
  - 1965 (Box 15)
  - 1968 (Box 15)
  - 1979 (Box 15)
  - 1980 (Box 15)
  - 1981 (Box 15)
  - 1982 (Box 15)
  - 1983 (Box 15)
  - 1984, 2 folders (Box 15)
  - 1985 (Box 15)
  - 1986 (Box 15)
  - 1987 (Box 15)
  - 1988 (Box 15)
  - 1989 (Box 15)
  - 1991 (Box 15)
  - 1992 (Box 15)
  - 1993 (Box 15)
  - 1994 (Box 15)
  - 1995 (Box 15)
  - 1996 (Box 15)
  - 1997 (Box 15)
  - 1998 (Box 15)
  - 1999 (Box 15)
  - 2000 (Box 15)
  - 2001 (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous calendar pages, undated (Box 15)
  - Address book, undated (Box 15)
- Photographs, circa 1890-1990s; Series V; 2 linear feet (2 boxes)
  Series V consists of photographs (including negatives) depicting Mary Barnard's family and travels.
  - Photograph albums, circa 1890-1990s; 9 (Box 16)
  - Photograph albums, circa 1890-1990s; 5 (Box 17)
  - Photographs and negatives, circa 1890-1990s; 5 (Box 17)
- Other Papers, 1933-2001; Series VI; 1.67 linear feet (3 boxes)
  Series VI consists of clippings and books, artwork by Mary Barnard, and audio and video cassettes.
  Organized into three subseries: Printed Material, Artwork, and Audiovisual Material.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Boxes 19, 20, and 25 contain audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Printed Material
    - Pages from clipping scrapbooks, 1976-1994; 7 (Box 18)
    - Clippings on Ezra Pound's death, 1971-1973 (Box 18)
    - Clippings on Ezra Pound, 1956-1975; 2 (Box 18)
    - Clippings of Mythmakers and Wasson pictures, undated (Box 18)
    - Clippings on Williams and Moore, 1974 (Box 18)
    - Miscellaneous clippings, undated; 8 folders (Box 18)
    - Anna Akhmatova poetry books, 1973, 1979; 2 folders (Box 18)
  - Artwork
    Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - Sawmill sketches, 1933-1936, undated (Box 18)
    - Watercolor paintings, undated; 2 folders (Box 18)
    - Collage, undated
    - "A Picture of the Moon," poster, 2001
    - Posters, 1984, undated
  - Audiovisual material
    Boxes 19, 20 and 25 contain audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - Gershefski's setting of Barnard's poem "Lai" (Pazmor) (Reinke) / "Man Overboard", undated; 1; 00:23:43; A high amount of hiss can be heard on the tape. The audio on the right channel is silent for the first four and a half minutes. (Box 25, Item barcode 39002104611273)
      Audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - Mary Barnard Profile, 1985 October; YCALMSS524_0001; 1; 00:07:28 (Box 25, Item barcode 39002102300010)
    - Mary Ethel Barnard, 1975 April 1; 1 (Box 19, Item barcode 39002104611281)
      A note details Mary Barnard reading her own poems. A list is included.
      Lethe
      Roots
      The Orchard Spring
      Shoreline
      Playroom
      Prometheus Loved Us
      Store
      The Rapids
      Adversity
      The Axe
      Note to a Neapolitan
      Encounter in Buffalo
      Dick
      Inheritance
      Midnight
      Martinsbrunn 1961
      The Pleiades
      The Spring
    - Gifts from the Muse, 1993; 1; 00:11:35 (Box 19, Item barcode 39002104611299)
      A list of contents is included with this audiocassette.
      Rollilia
      Mother of Song
      Stay With Me Now
    - Tom Vitale-Barnard, National Public Radio, 1986 October 7; 1; 00:06:51; Static can be heard on the tape. The program ends abruptly. (Box 19, Item barcode 39002104611307)
    - Songs of Sappho, 1986 January 21; 1; 00:39:30 (Box 19, Item barcode 39002104611315)
    - Ned Rorem/David Ward-Steinem, undated; 1; 00:39:12 (Box 19, Item barcode 39002104611323)
      Some Trees
      Little Elegy
      Night Crow
      The Tulip Tree
      Look Down
      Fair Moon
      What Sparkles
      Wiry Cries
      For Poulenc
      Fragments form Sappho
    - Mary Barnard, poetry reading on KOAR-FM, 1980 February 3; 1; 00:29:29; The program begins abruptly. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104611331)
    - Sappho and Aphrodite/Musical Selection, undated; 1; 00:54:03; The program is distorted at times. Hum and static can be heard on the tape. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104611349)
    - Tomas Svoboda. Journey, Cantata for Mezzosoprano, Baritone, Choir and Orchestra, undated; 1; 00:22:09; A high amount of hiss can be heard on the tape. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104611356)
    - Mary Barnard Memorial Service, 1st Presbyterian Church, Vancouver, WA, 2001 September 4; 1; 01:23:41; The program ends abruptly. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104611364)
    - National Public Radio Book Club, Sappho, 1999 April 22; 1; 00:50:52; The program begins and ends abruptly. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104611372)
- Oversize, 0.33 linear feet (2 boxes)
  - Photograph album (Series V.), circa 1890 (Box 22 (Oversize))
  - Photographs (Series V.), undated (Box 23 (Oversize))
  - Clippings (Series VI.), 1967-1986 (Box 23 (Oversize))
  - Watercolor paintings (Series VI.), undated (Box 23 (Oversize))
  - Collage (Series VI.), undated (Box 23 (Oversize))
  - "A Picture of the Moon," poster (Series VI.), 2001 (Box 23 (Oversize))
  - Poster (Series VI.), 1984 (Box 23 (Oversize))
  - Posters (Series VI.), undated (Box 24 (Broadside))